I have the development team, we have a lot of work with data, for example, we process
that not just blind data but also APIs like Google, Microsoft. So we are helping basically on
mainly on delivering some bespoke software like some internal tools.
And our colleagues also support them with some other things like scripts, for example,
and stuff. No, they also do that. Nowadays, a lot of people use AI, so it's kind of a lot of
like problem as well. And we basically are here to hire a new role for a senior software engineer.
If you could tell me what you do today. Okay. Okay. Now, well, I'm Vittem. I'm 43 years old already.
And I'm a software engineer. I used to have my own company. So I had close relationships with
companies and was more, yeah, more of a management going into the management roles and
that those kind of things. I'm a really, really big tech. How do you call it?
Yeah, I think I like to do all kinds of things. Going from simple, I'm currently building my own
security system with security cameras. And then I have to go into video decoding and that kind of
stuff to Kubernetes network and solutions and those kinds of things. So I'm a broad spectrum of
interests. So, yeah, I came across your, how did you say, go let's fake a C?
Yes, well, somebody asked me. So, and it really looked like a good job. So, yes, I
thought a little bit about what I'm going to tell you about what kind of things I do. I had some
projects in mind, but I don't want to steer this conversation or something. So, do you have some
questions maybe or what kind of person, because it?
Yeah, let me follow up. So, basically, my question is about, you said about your situation.
So, you are working on, but is it your personal or is your current work or what you currently do
actually? I'm actually currently without a job. So, I'm looking for a new job.
So, my question to you is actually our team, let's say, 12 people I believe or maybe 13.
And with, it's like, only we have one Dutch person there. The rest is different nationalities,
in me and Polish, for example, there's 13 people, Russian, Chinese, Swedish. So, we basically use
English as a primary language in our team, right? So, yeah, I wonder what you think about this,
because I think you have only a CV. I've seen Dutch on it and translated, but also what you think of
even though that, so our Amsterdam office is Dutch, and a lot of colleagues are Dutch there,
but even the developers and generally the communications are in English.
Yes. So, what do you think of that actually?
That's not a problem. I've had a few work environments that I had to talk English only.
So, I have experience with that. It's a little bit rusty right now, so.
I suspect that Dutch people are good at English, but I'm just wondering if you are okay with
or you, let's say, somehow we wouldn't be like this in my head.
No. You need to speak that, even though I speak English. That's great, if you are open to that.
And, yeah, I see that you had some freelancing, right, in your resume.
Yeah. Yeah, I didn't want to go and tell the whole life story, but, yeah.
Yeah, I started out at 12, age of 12 with programming. I wanted to
program the Lego technical Lego with the computer, so I wanted to basic, and I learned that myself.
After that, I wanted to do the actual education, the tech chef Matka, we call it IT.
So, I did the study, and then I went to go for a big of a teacher, because I got the opportunity
to become a DJ. So, I took it, and well, it wasn't really that financially liable, so I went back
into the IT, as well. There, I ended up with Microsoft Gold Partner. They did data sharing,
the lending people out to other companies. And so, I had got to see a lot of companies from
Insights. Also, there was an English assignment, so there I already got some experience with
the, with talking on English word development job. So, they went down because of the recession.
They didn't make it, so I got out of the job, and I started working at Autodatex. There was
more Windows Forms kind of applications, and with a really, really big database, so I learned all
the fine things of a database and large databases, and those kind of stuff.
And from there on, I went to move to Denhake here. I'm a kite surfer, so I'm really passionate about
kite surfing. And it was, yeah, I had to have a job here. I started working at a company that
dating sites. I'll just leave it at that. So, there was a really diverse environment. I had
to tend to build up a platform from scratch there, which became really, really big. We had like
millions of customers and really, really high turnout first. So, yeah, we had, like, yeah, I got
a press course in a huge traffic management. And from there on, my focus began to shift a little bit
because I became, I came at the level that programming isn't really the issue anymore.
It's more about handling the kind of traffic, handling, doing the delivery of the software.
So, I became a delivery manager in that company. And so, I did all the life going, we called it
back then. So, after that, I, because I'm surfer, surfer dude, so in the surf environment, I met a guy,
and he had a contract with Heineken. And he had to build an app for them. And he already had to
hold design. Everything was finished, but they couldn't get it in the app. So, I built a little
app for him in one evening. And after that, he, yeah, kind of told me, you have to quit your job
because I need to have an assignment. So, I began building apps for Heineken, Fumona.
And because that's really, it was all front-end stuff, you know, little texts, mostly CMS kind of
stuff. So, I started building my own platform to build the app. And I just to help me.
And I showed it to this friend of mine. And he was like, because Heineken at that moment had more
than 200 apps they had to make. And they used to have the folders, you know, that account managers
would go to the cafes and everything with a really big trunk full of folder and marketing material.
And they were in the transition tool, pushed it all away and go for full apps and everything
through tablets. And so, I got to demo the platform, the app development platform. And they took
it. And so, that was my flying start to my, yeah, the self-dependence, yeah, my own company.
And so, I had a really good start. But as you can understand, I built a platform to build apps.
And of course, that was really simple. And it was just basically like a sort of power point
for apps, you know. And so, I basically automated myself away. So, they hired somebody else to do my job.
Yeah. So, it wasn't really that, but yeah, I just didn't get the next 200 apps.
I didn't make that much money. So, I started looking for other companies. And I ended up with a
company that did medical equipment. They have like a webcam and it looks down and you fill
the pills for it in the hospital. And the webcam, real-time checks if everything is filled right.
So, there was with OpenCV, I don't know if you know that.
Oh, okay, well, OpenCV. So, it's like the same stuff that they used to make the Tesla's drive
and that kind of stuff. I did PowerQ that's a, they did this trading kind of thing. They bought
energy from the trading markets and then bought it in bulk for a lot of companies. So, they had
really good price. And they made this algorithm around this buying from the stock, from the market.
So, I had to basically pick that up and it was like a really old application that was working
with Excel as a database and everything. So, yeah, I kind of really put it up and went for
test-driven development and you know, build it up. So, it couldn't, couldn't ever go wrong or
something. And we had to really close the tile for like the financials. If we did a little change
to the algorithm, it needed to be historically correct, you know. So, we built this huge test
that we just continuously checked the outputs against the new changes and everything.
The integration test or end-to-end model unit test it was?
It was a combination of unit test and integration tests. So, I basically made it home, it
completely modular. So, I could just pull out the database and put it in Mark into it and
those kind of things. So, yeah, that's because I had my own company, I had to, and you know,
ensure the quality of code and everything myself. So, that really set my mindset to a different,
it's not like, we just built this feature and it's okay, you're also responsible for it and
you know, so it's really different approach. Yeah, that's, I have a lot, I can continue talking
with that. I have a lot of today. If I, this idea of like the low-code platform that I told you
about earlier, the app development platform, this idea and I've never really lost it. And today,
I'm building GRP, GRP, I don't know if you've seen it or might have linked it or anything.
Okay, well, it's like a combination of low-code and being able to just write your own code.
And I use Roslin code analyzers, I don't know if you know about them.
Yeah, so that allows me to basically take away all the fluff of programming, like
appy endpoints, I don't write them anymore, they get generated automatically. And like the front
end forms and everything, it's all automatically generated. So that helps me to,
yeah, it's basically reduce the code to Duplo, like like Legos, you know, the Duplo, the bigger
blocks for little children. Yeah, and yeah, I can just take, take, take, take and just
hook it up together and just have to fine tune it a little bit. And yeah, that helps me a lot
with the speed and those kind of things. Well, inside of those, because I'm talking about APIs now,
you can also do that for surface, like if you have like a really big micro surface architecture
or something like that, like surface discoveries, a really big thing in those kind of situations,
you can do those things to by using those kind of solutions. And yeah, I think it's like a whole
new dimension to programming, you know, it's a, you don't have to write generic classes anymore,
you just generate class, you know, so yeah, that's it. Or I'm wondering about sometimes it's not
about delivering the code, but also it's complying with some security, right? For example,
when you have endpoints, it's very easy to see what is your application above, but if you take
that away, let's say, do some dynamic generation, then it's going to be parallel to basically
describe what it is and therefore provide some security assessment, right? Because for example,
our organization, we get that kind of stuff to comply with, right? Yeah, there are certain
politics that sometimes you think this doesn't make sense to do, but we have to do it because of
the politics, right? We need to say, let's say, have some security layers in place. Oh yeah,
that's the biggest problem. If I can maybe, maybe stop you because the way I see it is like
totally the opposite because by using those, those analyzer generators, you get to make like
embed those weird security protocols and issues, you can embed those inside of the normal,
like it becomes the default way of working, you understand? So if I make a new surface,
like this, the front-end has to call a new surface or something like that and I generate the whole
the whole communication and it just generates it with all those weird security options and security
I say, how do you call it? It has to have this security measure the months, that's the word.
With the specific security months, because you don't really have to think about that inside of
your surface, it's just, it's done, it's already there and you don't have to think about it
anymore. But yeah, I really don't want to be gets into this kind of discussion because it's
also, you have to look for each thing, like the example I just gave, like what I just
basically did and made GRPC only with APIs. And yeah, so that's a good use case. Sorry.
Yeah, let's have a look deeper on this because I have also some other questions honestly about
not just technical because I see you are already dig in the technicalities, which is good, of course.
I have questions like a bit about way of work. So for example, like I mentioned, we have this team
and we have journalists there, we have media as well. You would be the senior,
as a viewer, not only you would be responsible for some knowledge with technical and skills,
but also guiding people and mentoring them and also resolving conflicts. So for example,
what would you do if some junior or a media would say that she doesn't or she doesn't want to use
your approach because you think it's great, well, they think something else is better, right?
You kind of cut me off before I could make the point that I don't want to make a big issue out
of it because you have to look for each, you know, I'm not trying to push anything, that's the
and that's also the thing I'm really worried about when I tell this story because people they
just like, whoa, don't know, that's way too advanced and that's not my thing. I just
I'm showing like the options I have. So if somebody comes to me and they say like, I want to do it
like this, do it like that. If you think it's better, show me. Then, no, yeah, I'm
what I was saying also that it doesn't mean they are right and let's say you are sure you are right
and they are wrong, but this is now about then being able to persuade them to your solution
because you know, if we do it the junior way, then it will fail and you will be responsible
as a senior that you allowed this right and you know this too. So this is this. Yeah, but that's
that's if it's if it's a junior, then it's like he needs this if I cannot persuade
the convincing of the of the thing, then he has to learn it himself. He has to make the mistake
himself and then usually they, you know, I cannot prove anything if it's not that if we're talking
about air, you know, so I just let it go. I just usually if this situation comes up, I would just
let it go and just move him by making the mistake, you know. So, but that's a junior and it's
really complex, of course. So, but yeah. In this world, what actually could happen,
to be honest, because we have those sometimes some pride in the team, you know, like different
mood, different day, but yeah, I get your point. Yeah, but it's not not written in law, of course.
This are really, you know, you have to or each situation and maybe maybe like like you say,
it's an ego thing, maybe you have to just sit down with him and just talk. There's something up,
there's yeah, the bad week or something and he just wants to talk, you know, it's you have to look
for each situation. So, I'm not like saying this is this is written in stone and this is the way
or something. I just really want to. Yeah. So, you're experienced, did you work in a bigger team,
let's say, where you've had this kind of stuff or yes. You were like most so developer.
No, with media blue, I worked with eight people and I was, of course, delivery manager,
slash tech, that's believe that something. So, I had these situations. I also have these
situations in really, really senior teams. So, yeah, I understand why you would ask some
question like this. So, yeah, but I was it. Well, I resolved it with worth, I would be sure
solved it really good. And it was I did pair programming with them and then we could just like
they needed that with my lost employee. Yeah, he was like really doing stuff with
GIT branching strategy. And do you know the GIT GIT? How do you call it?
GIT. You mean the kind of low level programming generation? No, no, no, I mean the branching
strategy, that's the word strategy. Yeah, sorry. Can I say GIT flow? Yeah, GIT flow, but they want to do
that you have like one branch and that's just like the the live branch. If you
pull requests towards it, it goes directly into the pipeline to go live.
And we use that, but we use honestly two, most in two environments, one only one,
development environment and production, right? Yes, thank you.
He wants to he wants to do it like this. And I understand that I've also read the DevOps book.
I've also worked within those trunk based deployments or something like that. But
the that that work what I did is they what he wanted to do is actually put the whole testing
face within your own development. You are responsible for your own testing and everything.
You have to just commit perfect code every time. And that's it can work with a lot of companies
they like a bold and calm or something like that that have like really a lot of front end
little changes and those kind of it. Yeah, why wait, you know, built built like a feature switch
into the code base and just switch it. And if it doesn't work, switch it back, you know,
it could work. But that only works if your code base has like zero books or
you know, like a very little books and very if it's really stable and if you have that really
good, but this this was like really buggy everything was broken basically. So yeah, that's I wanted
to steer him into like the normal get flow way of working. And it couldn't. He was like,
yeah, but that's possible. Forget it. And I was like, it doesn't mean you have to use it if it's
possible, you know. Yeah. I mean, that was a great opportunity to direct the
changes to only one production and nothing else in there. If it breaks your problem,
you must reverse it. Sometimes it can be irreversible and data division, let's say.
Yes, whatever. So yeah, but we for most products, we have that. Now, obviously, because
already I have a lot of my code, we start to have for those very small, we only want production
because it's very easy to test it and also very expensive if we have to do double environment
every single time, no matter what is the project. So we started a little bit shifting for the
small project to more approach, but that's not ideal, of course. And yeah, but we still prefer it
all the way. Yeah, well, it's it's kind of a hype thingy of like the last years that
to do it like this. But I also understand your situation. You have like a really like a like
basically only HTML. And yeah, he don't need a whole, you know, a whole pipeline set of first
iPad. I understand, but yeah. All right. I have also another question about
agency fit pretty much or this are all right, because I see that you are you are a lot of
old quality. Again, it is both. I also am like this. However, I wonder about what you think,
if you have really like a quick deadline, right? And you know, you cannot do it the way you want
to call it, let's say, a perfect call. Have you had to make some, yeah, sacrifices when you were
working and just do something technical, a lot of technical debt because it was the deadline.
Yes, I have. Yeah, we. So at media blue, it was like, we were just running and running and running.
And then. Yeah. So you have experience of also doing sometimes. Yeah. But that's
but I have also been in a situation where that went totally wrong. So
and you know, there's there's there's a certain level, then I'm going to say stop this in the
stop. So but that's I think if I can like detect with you, I think we're going to be on the same
level with that kind of stuff. All right. I got to hear. Yeah. We still have like a
10 minutes, a bit more. So I would like to go forward and build a very important topic actually
nowadays, which is the I I would like to know how do you what to do your day to day, how do you use
them more or less like right? I'm not I have this like kind of a ego thingy that I don't want to
pay for tokens. So I use all the free stuff that I can get. So I don't have like a cloud code
or something like that. But I do use anti-gravity and codex sometimes. Yeah. Like I said, I don't
I don't buy tokens. So it's really little little bit of use it. And I am yeah, I'm basically
I never been in the situation that I had to have, you know, that I could just offload everything
to AI. So yeah, I don't know how how other developers get into that kind of space because it's
so much faster if you just, you know, type it. And I've seen it with codex that I want I just
gave him a really big task. And he was just going for like two hours. And it was like what is he
doing, you know, it's yeah. So yeah, I don't know if you have any experience with that. But yeah.
For development, like I've been doing a lot of job hunting, of course. And so that kind of
scared me also to because all the governments and all those kind of organizations, they are all
moving away from the clouds nowadays. And they want to do a super run that they own their own data.
And it's not on the American server somewhere. So with debt in mind, I went to
specifically train myself into using a local AI's and using them as for the tool calling and
MCP kind of solutions. And yeah, try to focus on that. So, but of course, if it works there,
it works just to be. So there's no problem. But I, yeah, I'm really into the whole MCP tool calling
I basically made my own AI coding agent with built nets. So yeah, I like to
do. What you are prompting, because we said, Alex was working for two hours. So let's say
I want to use it as much as you use your own rights. So what you are prompting.
Now, well, well, my own is using Olama. So I don't know if you do, you know, Olama?
No, no, no, no, it's just a more than a year. Yeah, it's a local,
like Chatsichipi, which you install locally. So you have your own surfer inside of your computer,
you could just send messages and then it goes generate messages. But the models, they are
my computer, of course, is not that great. I just have a like six gigabyte of video memory. So
I'm not able to use the really good models, of course, but I wanted to make it so it could just
do stuff for me. That was the whole thing of the coding agent. The coding agent, if I hook it up
to Chatsichipi or Gemini or Cloud, of course, it will work. It will just code for me, just like
the codecs and just like all the other things. But this project was specifically for local AI's,
because you cannot, if you use like co-pilot or something in your first video, you cannot
hook that up to Olama, of course. So for that, I started to use it and yeah, I went way over the
board. So I'm making my own two calls and everything. So I'm deep in the whole thing. I see you look
like it. Don't know really what I'm talking about, the two calls, you know, what I mean with that.
No, what I'm wondering about is you said that you don't really like to use this other
reason, because they're taking talk and start. No, you are talking about it, right? And so I
wonder how is that helping you? Basically, what are the tasks that you are
delegating to that AI? All right, to get some Jardana, I'm just curious what kind of tasks
you do for yourself. For example, well, I don't really let AI write that much code for me.
The last thing I'm using a lot to call, right? I'm not going to lie, but I just curious,
because you don't say you don't use AI, you just use it, but I'm curious, what they
I asked for you like on day today, like creating files, please call the files or whatever, right?
No, the last the last thing I used AI for was to write a new client implementation
for chat to be for open AI for my client, my AI client. So I have a interface inside of my
my application, and it gets implemented by a few different clients. For example, the
Olamic client, and I made an open AI client, and now I made one, let AI make one with the new
Google thing, yeah, it's really good, the new Google AI, so I let it write its own implementation.
Yeah, so yeah, and it's basically I try to like use it as much as possible for the subtasks,
and like the all the in-between stuff, like the interface, and you know, that system that
that class is used by other modules, of course, in the system, and yeah, so yeah, I really don't
like I said, I have no experience with just handling off stuff the way I, it's a little bit old-school
but I did it, I did it of course, and I was like, whoa, oh, there goes my job, but yeah,
yeah, it makes mistakes, of course, so I was like, oh, sorry, yeah, you are in the hub, right?
Yeah, I have different shavings. So what do you think of commuting to Amsterdam?
The office is there. It's okay. I hope I don't have to be there every day, but yeah, it is true,
no, we have hybrid system, three, two times a week in the office, three should be, but we
honest in practice it's two times, and yeah, then three days or two days to move on,
okay, today I'm from home, yes, I see, for example, all right, now maybe the last part of this
interview, the questions from your side, and you ask already, let's do it officially too,
do you have questions? Yeah, what's, what kind of party did you last do within the company?
Can you explain a little bit about the problem and with the solution?
At the moment, we are honestly doing a lot of projects that are coming from our colleagues that
are quite cold at things. What do we do? We are helping them to foster, we are helping them to
pass security audit that is coming because our organization has to undergo security assessment
basically where they check everything, every requirement that is there and also will be
this in a couple of years, so yeah, we have them to first lift it from the laptop,
wipe code and solutions or some authorized unapproved clouds and put it in our
probe, yeah, approved cloud like Azure GCP, so you're really, really mopping after the AI stuff.
Yeah, yeah, now, but we also, of course, we are also having a lot of projects that are
products that are used, like we have some internal tools, or campaign management for
like data, visibility of clients in Google search, and other tools that are like things that
we build and we have to maintain that improve that and we are like because our team is not that big,
we know don't work on it every day and I mean part of the thing because let's say at the moment
one part of the thing is actually actively working on this, one of the projects, but
personally I'm now more delegated to do those AI, wipe code projects and we've been more stable,
so that's the part also we have some idea to make it more generic, like to provision it
faster, it might be similar to what you were doing, I have some ideas.
Okay, Azure or you do GCP, Microsoft call, and language on the other project.
Do you use surface buses and those kind of things?
Yeah, we use service bus, there is like from everywhere we speak a lot of functionality,
not everything of course, but definitely service bus, also on GCP we have data team that is
using that heavily, we are, I am personally not involved much with GCP, I mean I did one project
before then recently, the more serious project, but I was always a little bit involved
from just a bit back now, a bit more, we use BigQuery for example from the big data and stuff like that,
so yeah. Okay, that's one of those AI data store things,
BigQuery, I didn't understand, I didn't hear it.
No, BigQuery is the database basically, right, the big data and structure on SQL, however,
you can now have an agent out of the box supported by Google where you can simply
analyze your data and get some things using agent.
Yeah, okay, I was talking about this thing that if you go optimizing AI and stuff, you use
R-A-G and what it basically does is like this is a sort of AI that you can just push the prompt
into and that just tries to retrieve as much possible information about that topic,
the topics used in the prompt and I was, I thought that was that data thing that you mentioned,
so. No, we don't have to, like the colleagues I mentioned, they are using all these features
at the moment, so there are agents, they are being agents pretty much, right, and indeed they use that,
they use on GCP, WebEx, now it's renamed, and also on OpenAI, yeah, we use all kind of AI's
now we are building also the, yeah, for security, some consolidated approach to
call AI because it's out of control at the moment, everyone is calling it, and it's, yeah,
compliance, security, and also this kind of work I am now doing, yeah, it's kind of, yeah,
it's less exciting than building things, but we have to do this and I know,
hopefully, I don't even want to finance here. Well, yeah, it's, you know, I'm building my home,
home security thingy here, and I'm actually thinking about stuff like, oh, then the AI can just
automatically open the door and everything, and you go into that kind of, like the whole future
kind of thinking, like, yeah, that everything is done by robots, stuff, yeah, I hope, I hope we're not
making a big mistake by just helping them, you know, like the terminator that they all, you know,
made it possible, and then it was, everybody was just working for, this is going to work,
and this is going to help us, and yeah, then it turned on the
yeah, yeah, but I don't think LLM is going to be the thing that we'll do it, it's too
still too, yeah, unpredictable, still has limits, but even protocol, I have sometimes,
it just cannot do things, even though it's so hyped, yeah, it is amazing sometimes, but sometimes
also makes ridiculous choices, and I just cannot see a supervised way using an AI manager,
I don't know any idea about calling, and I'm going to build some, that's, I just don't see it.
At this moment in time, it's not existing, like the cloud, they are just handling the thing,
like, we have this problem, just put it all to the AI, and he's going to make all the choices
and everything, and yeah, that's not going to work. It's also expensive, right, because the credit's
aren't free, at least it was free, you could do what you said, like, it was working for two hours,
yeah, you come back, and well, if it's broken code, then you pay for it, the money, it was
cloud code, and who is the not pay for it, and those credit's are not cheap, so, yes,
couple hundred dollars, let's say, per week, and then some garbage code that you have to be
fucked for, you know, it's like, you just cannot do it that high level yet, the low level, I agree,
like, some testing, preparing some signatures of the tests, implementing small chunks,
for sure, optimizing telling you whatever, like, we use now AI, but I just don't, and
I call that solutions are cool, but then you have to, like, I have to now go through a lot of
crazy code that is repetitive, things instead of being like one function, it is duplication,
yes, yeah, it's pretty crazy, you know, but yeah, it works, it's impressive to the management,
because solution is there, it's cool idea, so expression of ideas is a really
hypervelocity, but the quality is really low, and yeah, I think a lot of work will be
at this stage, to optimize it, to lift and shift and improve, but who knows in the future,
I just think, at the moment, the email classes, more than that, it's great too, but
I think that like the AI, what's really good at is like,
making the bridge between humans and computers, so, yeah, it can understand,
understand you, so that's, and that's what, we are using it now like thinking computer or something,
but it's more of a tool that we can gap, we can use it to bridge the gap between computers and humans,
and yeah, we just, I think what we're doing with the coding agents, it works of course,
but it's not the usage, what we are going to use it for in the future, it's going to be like
reading emails and then just figuring out if you have to have a notification or something,
like really simple kind of tasks that humans used to do themselves, and they can now be lifted off
of your plate, you don't have to write that function anymore, it knows if you tell it what it has to do,
it knows what to build, but you cannot like say, okay, it built me this, and then it goes, you know,
you have to pull the strings, keep the strings in line or something or build barriers or whatever,
yeah, so, okay, yeah, I think the time is up, thank you for your time, yeah, it's been good talking
with you, and I think that I will, you know, have a right to keep in touch with you, okay,
yeah, and if you have any questions, let us currently, and yeah, we will be, yeah, reaching out
with the further process, okay, you, you cannot conclude it, you have to of course talk to other
people, I guess, so I'll hear it, it's been a nice conversation for me too, I have to, yeah, I'm a
little bit, with a headache, so I don't know, I normally am a little bit more exciting, so yeah,
that's, I hope you, I hope you, I hope you, I hope you, I talked to you later, okay, bye,